Records of Court Roma No. 153 (Bridgeport) Foresters of America
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
Records of Court Roma No. 153 (Bridgeport) Foresters of America
1870s-1960s
Court Roma No. 153 (Bridgeport) Foresters of America
BHC MSS 0014
5 linear feet 3.5 manuscript boxes 1 oversize box
Bridgeport History Center, Bridgeport Public Library
The Foresters of America (now Foresters Financial) were a fraternal society with an emphasis on providing for members when they were in ill health or when they died. Court Roma No. 153 served Bridgeport's Italian American community, and the records document the members of the organization and their activities.
Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Nicolas Pasquariello in 2009. Originally accession 2009.02.
Historical Note
Established in Philadelphia in 1832, the Foresters of America was originally an offshoot of the English organization the Ancient Order of Foresters, originally founded in 1745. According to the Ancient Order, the fraternity goes back to the days of Robin Hood, but this is a foundational fabrication. Regardless, Robin Hood is invoked in group rites and events frequently. The American order had a "Supreme Court" in each state, and individual groups were called "courts" rather than lodges. In 1889, the Foresters of America broke off from their English counterpart and gained independence.
By joining the Foresters of America, members were able to ensure that they would have some form of income should they fall sick, make sure that they and their spouses would be buried, and ensure that relatives would be provided for in death. As a result, the organization has survived to become Foresters Financial, which provides financial planning to this day.
Present in the collection is the material relating to the Bridgeport court, called Court Roma. Bridgeport had nine courts in total including Court Roma, Court Iranistan (No. 34), Court Marina (No. 53), Court Pequonnock (No. 62), Court Nathaniel Wheeler (No. 92), Court Park City (No. 99), Catalpa Circle (No. 14), Star of Pembrook Circle (No. 177 Lady Foresters of America), Catalpa Circle (No. 425 Lady Foresters of America), and Lucette Warner Circle (No. 472 Lady Foresters of America).
The designation Court Roma, versus the others which are specific to Bridgeport locales, suggests that it was meant to serve the Italian community. This is furthered by the fact that the only names present within the applications are Italian, and there is correspondence with other Italian organizations. Immigrants joining fraternal organizations for benefits like those listed above was a logical choice. As such, the Court Roma documents offer insight into the members of the Bridgeport Italian community at the time.
Scope and Content of Collection
The immigrant experience within Bridgeport is a story told over and over again by various communities that have called the city home. Fraternal organizations such as the Foresters of America helped to provide a network of support for the community, and Court Roma in Bridgeport represents a unique view into the Italian American community of Bridgeport from the 1880s to the 1950s. The bulk of the records compromise the 1900s-1920s, and give the names of countless Italian immigrants and Italian Americans who called the city home at the start of the 20th century.
Arrangement
The first series, general information and overview, provides information about the Foresters within Bridgeport, along with reports and information about their financial status. The second and largest series is the membership applications, which arrived at the Bridgeport History Center in alphabetical order. That order has been maintained. Series III represents correspondence from Court Roma over the years, with series IV representing the only existing minutes in the series.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Foresters of America; Bridgeport (Conn.); Fraternal organizations; Italian American men; Italian American experience
- Series I, General information and overview
  - Court Roma no. 153 Constitution and By-Laws, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - By-Laws of the Foresters of America Grand Court of Connecticut, 1936-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Roll book, 1919-1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Court Roma no. 153 minutes, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Auditor’s Reports, 1942-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Auditor’s Reports, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reports for Court Roma no. 153 and USA No. 460, 1935-1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Report on committee for an excursion, July 1, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anniversary commissions, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II, Membership applications
  - Blank membership application, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Blank application for reinstatement, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, A, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, B, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, C, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, D, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, E, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, F, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, G, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, I, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, L, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, M, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, N, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, O, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, P, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, R, 1870-1939 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, S, 1870-1939 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, T, 1870-1939 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Membership applications to Court Roma no. 153, U and V, 1870-1939 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Foresters of America certificates, 1910-1919 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series III, Correspondence
  - Bulletins from the Grand Court of Connecticut, 1935-1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Supreme Court of Connecticut, 1936-1942 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Board of Management for Connecticut, 1934-1942 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Aldo Lardorei, 1936-1941 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with John J. Ciullo, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with Amendo Giannttasio, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with Thomas M. Donnelly National Memorial Association, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with other Italian organizations, 1936-1941 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1954, 1939-1959 (Box 4, Folder 1-7)
- Series IV, Minutes
  - Minutes, 1945-1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)